Hussain Mahfood Al-Kamel

Personal Information

- Nationality: Bahraini
- Contact Number: +973 36300222
- Email: hussain@mahfood.ws

Summary

Technical Leader with more than 20 years of experience working in technology in a variety of industries, including financial, retail, and logistics sectors, as well as government and semi-government. Convert difficult projects, particularly those involving software and hardware, into successful deliveries at local and regional locations.

Experience

Freelancer (2022 - Present)

- Lead ERP Implementations
- Develop Effective Business Intelligent Analytics and Insights
- Provide Artificial Intelligent / Deep Learning Solutions
- Build Cloud Systems (Private/Public/Hybrid/SaaS) with Amazon Web Service and Microsoft Azure and Office 365
- Development Web and Mobile Applications

Head of PMO & Business Applications – International Payment Services (June 2023 – August 2023)

- Manage the delivery of Five Projects across Four Client engagements
- Lead ERP Implementation
- Worked with IT to resolve Security Issues discovered by Penetration Test
- Evaluated IT Strategic Options for On-Premises, Cloud or SaaS deployment
- Acted as a Business Development Representative

Senior Manager IT & I4.0 - BFG International (2017 – 2022)

- Lead Industry 4.0 Project
- Build new infrastructure with security, reliability, and availability (Microsoft, Cisco, VMware & Ruckus)
- Implement a new ERP system (epicor)
- Used Artificial Intelligent in Planning with a Deep learning (Azure, AWS and Python)
- Evaluate Indoor Positioning and Tracking systems (UWB, Bluetooth and RFID)
- Industrial Internet of Things (IIOT) (Sensors, Custom Electronics Boards & handheld devices
- Augmented/Assisted Reality Solution (Microsoft Hololens)
- Autonomous machines (CNC and KUKA Robotics)
- Visualization and Dashboard (PowerBI and Custom Web Application)
- Al Optimization Project Management between QiO and Sulb

IT Senior Executive - Economic Development Board (2005 – 2017)

- Manage IT team members
- Manage the implementation of new and revised systems.
- Develops technical standards and procedures documentation for systems design, maintenance, and operation.

- Develops cost estimates for new hardware and software applications necessary to maintain a healthy computing environment in term of performance and availability.
- Plan, test, recommend, and implement servers, network, workstations and storage hardware and software.
- Serve as technical specialist in systems problems and emergencies, work with vendors to resolve complex systems problems and recommend solutions for short-, medium-, and long-range projects.
- Consult with users and evaluate requirements, recommend designs, provide cost analyses, plan projects, and coordinate tasks for installation of data systems.
- Conducts feasibility studies to identify ways of improving the efficiency and effectiveness of data center servers and systems.

IT Consultant and Project Manager (as secondment) - Ministry of Finance (Aug 2010 – Dec 2010)

- Enhance Bahrain government financial system licenses (Oracle E-Business Suite)
- Disaster recovery implementation
- ISO 27001 information security standard
- Align IT Strategy with e-Government strategy
- Manage to upgrade IT systems (email, databases, websites (intranet and internet), firewalls and servers virtualization)
- Restructure datacentre to be environmentally friendly
- Introduce services using cloud computing Azure and AWS

Network Implementation Administrator - PWCLogistics(Agility) (2003 – 2005)

- Implementing IT systems in Bahrain, Kuwait, Qatar, Saudi Arabia and Jordan Branches
- Use Microsoft technologies such as Active Directory 2000/2003, Windows 2000, NT4,Exchange 2000/2003, MS-SQL,ISA, Share Point, Oracle 7, Oracle 8i, IIS Web server, FTP server, DNS server and Telnet servers & replication
- Maintaining Backup, Antivirus and IT asset management systems
- Implementation helpdesk system
- Configuration of the Cisco Firewall, Router and Switches
- Maintain Wireless system with the inventory of the handheld devices
- Setup Voice over IP for international calls
- Installation of VPN server for remote access to the users
- Installation of the new hardware and software
- Support users with the business applications
- Implement UPS systems for power backup
- Maintaining Samsung PABX system with call monitoring
- Installation of the time attendance systems

Network Support Engineer - Arab Financial Services (AFS) (1999 - 2003)

- Support Banks over the phone or onsite visit
- Installation of the servers like (Exchange, Proxy, SNA, Backup, Domain, DNS, RAS, Symantec NAV, Veritas Backup Exec, Linux (Red hat) and UNIX (Sun Solaris)
- Checkpoint Firewall installation and configuration
- Support Clients PCs with different operating systems (MS-Win9x, WinNT4, MS-Win200, Windows XP. Linux and UNIX.

- Installation of the new Hardware and Software
- WAN support (Routers, Leased Lines, Extranet, Visa and MasterCard networks) on Ethernet and Fibre optic
- Programming in Visual Basic, HTML and Crystal Report and Publishing the Web Site to the Internet
- Mainframe connection with the LAN Ethernet over (TCP/IP or Token Ring) and Cabling and Network Points
- Support and customize Mainframe (Z/OS and VSE/ESA) operating systems with (ES\9000, H30 and Z\800 series) hardware with CICS Cobol with VisionPlus Application
- Replace old IBM routing systems with Cisco routers
- Manage Controllers with coax connections to the computers and PC board emulators
- Credit Cards Embossing

IT Technician and Sales (Part-time) - (Delmon Information Technology, Virtual Technologies and SAMA Al-Computer) (1995 -1999)

- Assemble and fix personal computers
- Routers and modems configurations
- Servers installation and configurations
- Software installations

Education & Trainings

2023 - Thomson Reuters

- Financial Crime (Middle East)
- Operational Risk Management Essentials

2023 (12 Weeks Bootcamp) - General Assembly

- Software Engineering Immersive
 - Languages (Python, JavaScript)
 - Backend Systems (NodeJS, Express, Django)
 - Frontend Systems (React, Flutter, Bootstrap, jQuery, Ajax, Axios API, HTML, CSS)
 - Databases (SQL and NoSQL)
 - Operating Systems (Shell Scripting in Linux, Mac and Windows)
 - o Tools (Github version control, Microsoft Visual Studio ide)

2019 - Amazon at BIBF

AWS Certified Solutions Architect

2016 - VMware

NSX vSphere: Install, Configure, Manage V5

Knowledge Village – Dubai, United Arab Emirates

2016 - BIBF

Effective Business Correspondence

2015 - Microsoft

Microsoft Certificate system Associate - MCSA

SQL Database Administrator- DBA

2015 - Microsoft

SharePoint Administration – intranet and intranet portal

Configure and Administrating MS SharePoint

2014 - ISO 27001:2013

Lead Implementer – Information Security Management System

BSI - British Standard Institute - Bahrain eGoverment

2012 - VMware

VMware vSphere: Install, Configure, Manage V5

Knowledge Village - Dubai, United Arab Emirates

2011 - Microsoft

MCITP Server Administrator

CIO - Bahrain

2008 - Cisco

Cisco Certified Network Associate

Cisco - United State

2008 - Leaders

Information Technology Infrastructure Library (ITILv3)

EXIN - United State

2008 - Arab Open University

BSc in Business Administration*

2007 - The Leadership Trust (UK)

Leadership In Management Program

2006 - IIR (UAE)

Business Intelligent

2006 - Foundry Networks

- Core and edge switches
- Applications load balancer

2003 - Creative Knowledge

Future IT

2002 - BIBF

- Everything You Need to Know About Supervision
- Leadership Skills
- Communicating With Confidence

2002 - GBM (IBM)

- An Introduction to the Z/OS and OS/390 Environment
- Fundamental System Skills in Z/OS and OS/390
- Z/OS and OS/390 system Operations
- Z/OS and OS/390 J.C.L and utilities

2001 - New Horizon

- MCSE (Microsoft Certified System Engineering)
- MCP (Microsoft Certified Professional)

2001 - New Horizon

A+ Plus Certificate in Software and Hardware

COMPTIA - United State

1999 - ALBA

Training Technician (Instrumentation Department)

1999 - Bahrain Training Institute

National Diploma in Instrumentation and Process Control Engineering - BTEC - UK

Skills

- IT Solution Architecture (Hardware and Software)
- Cloud Administration (Amazon AWS and Microsoft Azure/ Microsoft 365)
- Servers and Desktop OS (DOS, Unix, Linux Distributions- Ubuntu, MAC OS and Windows)
- Mainframe (OS administration, connectivity and host integration system)
- Microsoft Servers (Hyper-V virtualization, Group policy, KPI certificates, Domain controllers, Domain names, DHCP, VPNs, IIS, FTP, Print services, Share folders, WSUS Patching system, Virtual Desktops, IAS and ADFS)
- Microsoft Systems (Office365, Exchange, Dynamics CRM, SharePoint, SQL DBA, PowerBI)
- Cisco (Routers, Firewall, Access points, Switches, UCS (blades and servers), IP phones (UC voice and video), IronPort email filtering)
- VMware (Server virtualization, Desktop virtualization, Application virtualization, VCloudAir with failover and back, NSX virtual network)
- Storage systems (EMC and NetApp)
- Firewalls (Fortinet, Untangle and Cyberoam)
- Wireless (Ruckus, Dragonwave, Ubiquiti and Foundery AP + Switches)
- Proxy and Caching engine (Blue Coat and Foundry Load Balancer)
- Antispam and Antivirus Systems (Kaspersky, Symantec and Ironmail)
- Backup Systems and Monitoring (Veeam, Veritas and CA BrightStor) with Automated Tape Library (HP, Dell and IBM)
- Helpdesk and Monitoring System (ManageEngine, PRTG Paessler)
- Programming in New and Old Languages such as Clipper, dbase, Access, Visual Basic
- Others (Wireshark network troubleshoot and auditing, 802.1x network authentication implementation, pdq deploy Application deployment, Acronis OS image deployment, Video streaming, CCTV, Satellites, security systems and Access control systems)

Languages

English and Arabic

Interest

Technology Research and Sports